Guide to the Randolph Linsly Simpson African-American Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Series I. Visual Material
  - CABINET PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Pach, New York Cameo portrait of Mary Ann Wolker; elderly lady in white cap. In ink on mat beneath photograph, "'Mary Ann' Amherst" In ink, on mat to right, "Dear old Mary Ann had the care of students' rooms in colleges for many years. Many an hour she has spent in my rooms at the Dake House cracking jokes. My last day in Amherst she spent in my big sleepy hollow chair watching me pack up." Framed cabinet photograph, 1883
      Item #238.2
      This and Item #238.1 are matted together and from the same frame. In ink on small piece of paper tucked into mat, "Amherst College Year Book Class of 1884 Property of J.W. North, 267 5th Ave. NYC, 1923"
    - Biddle Artistic Photographer, Xenia, OH, 1897
      The following fourteen exterior view photographs of the campus and faculty homes of Wilberforce University were all taken by the same photographer. Cabinet photographs.
      Recto each in pencil, "Taken 1897." All photographs are matted in a single frame; from top left down and then right:
      Item #239 (1-14)
      - 1. Exterior view Mitchell Avenue; medium view of row of houses on opposite side of tree lined dirt road. Stamped recto along base of photograph, "MITCHELL AVENUE, WILBERFORCE UNIVERSITY."
      - 2. Close view, large two story house; two adults, three children standing and seated at corner.
      - 3. Exterior view of "Mrs. M. Davis" and house. Large two story house, woman stands in foreground, boy seated on windowsill behind. In ink, recto, at base of photograph,"Mrs. M. Davis."
        Verso, in pencil, "Lavinia Davis house W.O." Below, in ink, different hand, "And Ross Home, Terrie Ann Ingles (rest obscured by mat)."
      - 4. Exterior view, Elmwood Cottage. Two story house; four people, two standing, two seated on covered porch. Printed recto along base of image, "ELMWOOD COTTAGE. Residence of Prof. T.H. Jackson, Wilberforce, Ohio."
      - 5. Two story house with balcony above covered porch; girl sits with dog on porch. Stamped in ink, recto, along base of photograph, "Residence of J.A. Clark, Esq., Wilberforce, Ohio."
      - 6. Group photograph, Mrs. Emma Anderson and Mrs. Knight. Two women, one standing, one seated with child on lap, second child sits on doorstep, all on small covered porch. In ink, recto, at base of photograph, "Mrs Emma Anderson & Mrs. Knight."
        Verso, in pencil, "Miss Young's house"
      - 7. Shorter Avenue, dirt road with houses on right; figure stands in doorway of nearest house. Printed, recto, along base of photograph, "SHORTER AVENUE, WILBERFORCE UNIVERSITY."
        Verso, in pencil, "20 min. to 3 A.M. May 24th '89."
      - 8. Exterior view, residence of Bishop J.A. Shorter. Two story house, balcony with fancy railing above covered porch; two adults seated in chairs, two children seated at top of porch steps. Printed, recto, along base of photograph, "Residence of Bishop J.A. Shorter, Wilberforce, Ohio."
      - 9. Exterior view Sunnyside Cottage; two story house with balcony above covered porch along three sides of building. Stamped recto at base of photograph, "SUNNY SIDE COTTAGE. Residence of President S.T. Mitchell, Wilberforce, Ohio."
      - 10. Exterior view Payne Avenue. Tree lined dirt road leads to University building set among the trees. In ink, recto, at base of photograph "Payne Ave."
      - 11. Exterior view; large two story house behind trees; covered balcony above covered porch; both with columns; five adults and four children stand and sit on or near porch. In ink, recto, at base of photograph, "I/J? P. Shorter's."
      - 12. Exterior view of Shelton Morris' Home with smaller buildings attached. Sign above attached building, "GROCERY & PROVISION STORE." Three men stand in front. In ink, recto, along base of photograph, "Shelton Morris home."
      - 13. Exterior view, residence of Mrs. N.J. Rouse and Mrs. M.J. Carr." Two story house, covered porch, painted white fence. Printed recto along base of photograph, "Residence of Mrs. N.J. Rouse and Mrs. M.J. Carr, Wilberforce, Ohio."
      - 14. Exterior view Pleasant Hill Cottage; two story house, man stands on covered porch; stamped recto along top of image, "PLEASANT HILL COTTAGE, Residence of Mr. H.C. Clay and Mrs. Dr. M.R. Delany, Wilberforce, Ohio."
    - Gentile, Photos and Studios, Lydian Art Gallery, 103 State Street, Chicago; Proprietor, Lydia J. Cadwell Bust portrait of Frederick Douglass, facing right. Cabinet photograph, circa 1875 (Box 9, Folder 286)
      In ink, verso: "March 26, 1881." Unusual to find a lady photographer at this period.
      Item #244
    - Studio unknown Bust portrait of Frederick Douglass, facing left. Cabinet photograph, circa 1875 (Box 9, Folder 287)
      Verso, in colored pencil: "Frederick Douglass 1817(sic)-1895, son of slave --Anti-Slavery lecturer."
      Item #245
    - C.M. Bell, Artist, Washington, D.C. Bust length portrait of Frederick Douglass, facing slightly right. Cabinet photograph, circa 1890 (Box 9, Folder 288)
      Item #246
    - Falk, 949 Broadway, NY Bust length portrait of Henry Ward Beecher, preacher and abolitionist. Cabinet photograph, circa 1875 (Box 9, Folder 289)
      Item #1965
    - Clark Photograph Co., Memphis, TN Half length formal portrait of a man with prominent stick-pin and watch chain, Cabinet photograph, circa 1880 (Box 9, Folder 290)
      Item #1966
    - Evans, Chicago Bust length formal portrait of W.W. Keeble. Cabinet photograph, 1886 June 18 (Box 9, Folder 291)
      In ink, verso: "Yours Truly, W.W. Keeble, June 18th, 1886"
      Item #1967
    - Mahon and Taylor, Nashville, TN Three quarter length formal portrait of young lady in bridal gown; lace veil in background. Cabinet photograph, circa 1880 (Box 9, Folder 292)
      Item #1968
    - The New York Photograph Gallery, Petersburg, VA Young child standing, wearing bow tie, fitted shirt, pleated skirt, pantaloons, high leather shoes and black stockings; hand rests on some sort of prop on a grassy covered table. Cabinet photograph, 1888 (Box 9, Folder 293)
      This studio is known to have been owned by black photographers.
      Item #2063
    - Unknown photographer Young lady standing by chair draped in flowered cover. Cabinet photograph, circa 1895 (Box 9, Folder 294)
      Item #2064
    - Sarony, 37 Union Square, New York, NY Half length portrait of Matilda Sissieretta Jones, known as "the Black Patti;" woman in a fancy dress leaning on a pedestal, bosom festooned with medals, Cabinet photograph, circa 1895 (Box 9, Folder 295)
      Verso, in pencil: "Sissaretta Jones the black Paddy (sic) entertainer, leader of a musical company." Another print, from the Meserve Collection, is in the Wadsworth Atheneum's Amistad Foundation Collection.
      Item #2075
    - Eisenmann, Photo Artist, New York Young man holding crippled man, Cabinet photograph, 1890 (Box 9, Folder 296)
      In pencil, upper right hand, verso: "10/21/90" The photographer was known for his unusual subjects.
      Item #2121
    - New York Art Gallery, Richmond, VA Young man in white shirt and coat. Cabinet photograph, circa 1885 (Box 9, Folder 297)
      Item #2122
    - Rice, 1217 & 1219 Penna. Avenue, Washington, D.C. (Successor to Alexander Gardner) Young black woman holding white child in lap. Cabinet photograph, undated (Box 9, Folder 298)
      Item #2123
    - Brady & Co., Washington, D.C. Alexander H. Stephens and servant (former slave). Cabinet photograph, circa 1875 (Box 9, Folder 299)
      Provenance: Frederick Hill Meserve; George R. Rinhart.
      Item #2124
    - A.M. Riser, Artist, No. 20 Plain Street, Columbia, SC Full length oval portrait of Rev. George David standing with right hand extended and an open book in left hand. Cabinet photograph, circa 1870 (Box 9, Folder 300)
      Verso in pencil: "Rev. George David is Pastor of Col" Rev. David was pastor of colored church.
      Item #2125
    - J.W. Rothwell, Washington, PA Full length portrait: barefoot boy wears hat, torn shirt, pantlegs rolled up, stands beside balustrade and holds violin. Cabinet photograph, undated (Box 9, Folder 301)
      Item #2126
    - J.E. Read, successor to Headley & Read, 5 Purchase St., New Bedford, MA Double portrait of Frederick Douglass, seated, with Joseph Douglass, grandson standing with violin. Cabinet card, 6-3/8 x 4-1/4, undated (Box 9, Folder 302)
      Item #2199
    - Rice, Washington D.C. Bust length portrait of man with mutton chop sideburns in suit looking right. Cabinet photograph, undated (Box 9, Folder 303)
      Verso, in ink: "Charles R. Douglass Youngest son of F.D."
      Item #2202
    - Bishop, Washington D.C. Oval portrait of Rosetta Douglass Sprague, Woman with white hair, wearing dress with mutton sleeves, fancy lace scarf at neck, clasp with photograph of man in uniform with sash and medals also at neck. Cabinet Photograph, 1893 May 12 (Box 9, Folder 304)
      In ink, recto, beneath photograph: "Affectionately, Your Sister, Rosetta" Verso, ink, same hand: "To Lewis H. Douglass, May 12/93" Verso, different ink, different hand: "Rosetta Douglass Sprague (Daughter of F. Douglass + Anna Murray D.)"
      Item #2203
    - Lloyd, Troy, NY Full length portrait of a lady standing with arms folded in front of her, left elbow and right hand on elaborate chair back to her left. Imperial cabinet photograph, circa 1890 (Box 10, Folder 305)
      Item #230
    - A.P. Gates' New Gallery, Charleston, WV Full length portrait of a lady standing with right arm on newel post. Imperial cabinet photograph, circa 1890 (Box 10, Folder 306)
      Item #231
    - Norman, Natchez, MS Full length portrait; young man in frogged band uniform holding cornet; kepi with "SCR" in wreath; elaborate fireplace set. Imperial Cabinet photograph, circa 1890 (Box 10, Folder 307)
      Item #232
    - C. Eisenhardt's Art Gallery, Detroit, MI Full length portrait, man in lodge uniform, feathered fore and aft cap, sword, standing in forest set. Imperial Cabinet photograph, circa 1890 (Box 10, Folder 308)
      Item #233
    - Bailey & Murphy, no location Full length portrait, old man with beard and eye patch, standing, in very tattered greatcoat, large scarf, and woolen stocking cap, bandaged hands and feet, holding rough walking stick in left hand; depicted in set before rustic gate. Matted cabinet photograph, circa 1895 (Box 10, Folder 309)
      Item #234
    - J. H. Kent, Photographer, 24 State Street, Rochester, N.Y. Cameo portrait of Frederick Douglass, looking right. Studio photograph. 9-1/4 x 6-1/2, circa 1892 (Box 10, Folder 310)
      Identified in pencil recto within photo, beneath figure. Autograph? "With compliments to my dear friend Miss Anthony, J. H. Kent" in pencil, verso, top. "Died Feb. 20, 1895" underlined in ink, verso, left below pencil inscription.
      This presentation photo of Douglass appears to have been presented by the photographer to Miss Susan B. Anthony (1820-1906) of Rochester, N.Y., abolitionist and suffragette. Miss Anthony showed Mr. Douglass to his seat when he arrived, on the afternoon of February 20, 1895 at the Washington D.C. Women's Convention. It is suggested that the ink inscription on the verso might be that of Miss Anthony herself.
      Item #247
    - Rice, Washington, D.C. Oval Portrait of Blanche Kelso Bruce in suit, looking right. Matted cabinet photograph., circa 1870 (Box 10, Folder 311)
      Accompanying documentation identifies Bruce as former VA slave who escaped to the North, studied at Oberlin, and be came a planter in MS; had been a tax collector, sheriff, and school superintendent before election to Senate at age 33.
      Item #2120
    - Un-numbered Items, undated (Box 10, Folder 312-313)
      Includes 2 unidentified cabinet photographs.
  - CARTES DE VISITE
    Cartes de visite include more than two hundred images spanning circa 1860 to 1890. These include portraits of Frederick Douglass and members of his family; the sculptor Edwina Lewis; and the actor Ira Aldridge. John R. Lynch, speaker of the House of Representitives in Mississippi and one of the first black members of the Reconstruction cabinet, is also identified, as is Josiah Thomas Walls, the first black member of the House of Representitives during Reconstruction. An image of Sojourner Truth by Van Doorn, 1863, is, according to R. L. Simpson, possibly the first published photograph of the subject. Among the Civil War cartes de visite is a field shot of the Seventh New York Regiment, identified as the work of George Barnard. Also present are images of black entertainers, possibly including the Hampton Jubilee Singers who toured American and Europe, as well as other unidentified singers, dancers, instrumentailists, and named figures such as Zumigo the Magician.
    The Duchess of Sutherland, supporter of Frederick Douglass, is represented in a carte de visite taken in London. Other British subjects include the dramatist Dion Boucicault, producer of the anti-slavery play, "Octoroon," and abolitionist George Thompson. Other white subjects include anti-slavery lecturer Anna Elizabeth Dickenson; Tom Thumb and his wife Lavinia, pictured with their black servant; and Lucretia Mott, feminist and leader in the abolitionist movement. Several white officers assigned to black military units are identified. The cartes de visite also portray black nursemaids with the white children for whom they cared.
    Among the exterior views is a Brady photograph of the "slave-pen" in Alexandria, Virginia, dated 1862, and scenes of slave cabins located in Helena, Arkansas. Considered rare by the collector is an 1867 outdoor street scene in Kansas taken by an unknown photographer. A set of undated photographs from the Oak Gallery, Memphis, Tennesee, provides images of Jefferson Davis's house, and the "Contraband Yard," among other locations.
    Included with the portraits of many individuals is anecdotal material found by the collector, such as newspaper clippings. The presence of such material is noted.
    - C.M. Marsh, Photographer, Canandaigua, NY Young lady standing by fancy chair, wearing gold chatelaine. Carte de visite, circa 1875 (Box 11, Folder 314)
      Item #D-1
    - Beardsley Bro's Art Gallery,72 & 74 Oswego Street, Ithaca, NY Elderly lady seated, wearing white bonnet. Carte de visite, circa 1875 (Box 11, Folder 315)
      Item #D-2
    - Bogardus Galleries, 872 Broadway, Corner 18th Street, New York, NY Bust portrait, James R. Priest. Carte de visite., circa 1875 (Box 11, Folder 316)
      "James R. Priest" in ink verso. Same image as D-58.
      Item #D-3
    - Studio unknown Young man with moustache, standing by chair, hat in hand. Carte de visite, circa 1870 (Box 11, Folder 317)
      Item #D-4
    - Studio unknown Lady standing by pillar. Carte de visite, circa 1870 (Box 11, Folder 318)
      Item #D-5
    - Revenaugh, Ann Arbor, MI Bust portrait, elderly lady with braids and chain necklace. Carte de visite, circa 1885 (Box 11, Folder 319)
      Item #D-6
    - W. E. Burroughs, successor to Bundy & Williams, 158 Main Street, Middletown, CT Cameo portrait, young lady with long curls and finger on chin. Carte de visite, circa 1875 (Box 11, Folder 320)
      Item #D-7
    - Nims, Photographer, Fort Edward, NY Bust portrait of elderly lady, wearing brooch, earrings and ribbon at collar. Carte de visite, circa 1875 (Box 11, Folder 321)
      Identification number "28017" in pencil verso.
      Item #D-8
    - J. Taylor's Photographic Studio, 189-191 Sixth Avenue, corner 13th Street, New York, NY Double portrait of Florence Munsell and Diana; young white girl facing front seated on high object, attended by black lady with colorful outfit and fanciful bandanna in profile; Hand tinted Carte de visite, circa 1868 (Box 11, Folder 322)
      Subjects identified in pencil verso. Large portion of 2-cent revenue stamp verso.
      Item #D-9
    - Richardson, Photographer, New York, NY Bust portrait of lady with fancy bow tie. Carte de visite., circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 323)
      "Mary Ellen" in pencil verso.
      Item #D-10
    - W.P. Kendall, Photographer, Woodstock, VT Full length portrait, young girl standing by tasseled chair, holding doll and handle of doll carriage. Carte de visite, circa 1870 (Box 11, Folder 324)
      Item #D-11
    - Slee Brothers, "Po'Keepsie," NY Full length portrait, man with beard standing with hand on chair, checkered pants, vest with gold chain. Carte de visite., circa 1870 (Box 11, Folder 325)
      Identification stamped recto, below photograph. Verso, in pencil: "5735"
      Item #D-12
    - S.Y. Richards, Photographer, Main Street, Carbondale, PA Three quarter length portrait of Dan Walker seated wearing three piece suit, fancy light vest with gold chain. Carte de visite., circa 1870s (Box 11, Folder 326)
      Identified verso, in pencil: "Dan Walker of Carbondale, Pa."
      Item #D-13
    - B. P[eter] Paige, Plumbe Gallery, Washington, D.C. Full length portrait of Mrs. Washington; elderly lady wearing apron and cap, standing with cane, next to elaborate side chair. Carte de visite, circa 1859 (Box 11, Folder 327)
      In pencil, verso: "Mrs. Washington; reputedly servant to Mrs. George Washington. Note: From an important Virginia photo album with Custis photographs."
      Item #D-14
    - George Goodman, Portrait and Landscape Photographer, Fort Hill, Margate (England), Established 1858. Three quarter length portrait of Uncle John; man with bushy moustache in white suit, gold chain, medals, and fancy hat, holding fiddle. Carte de visite., circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 328)
      Subject identified in pencil, verso. Studio stamped verso.
      Item #D-15
    - Barnard, successor to S. T. Souder, Photographer, No. 263 King Street, Charleston, SC Half length portrait, elderly lady seated wearing plaid white shawl and bandanna. Carte de visite, circa 1868 (Box 11, Folder 329)
      Item #D-16
    - Bartlett & Webster, Photographic Artists, 297 Main Street, over State Bank, Hartford, CT Full length portrait, young lady seated in fancy chair, fingerless net gloves. Carte de visite, circa 1868 (Box 11, Folder 330)
      Item #D-17
    - Wm. F. Douglass, Photographer, Rooms over Post Office, Guilford, CT Half length portrait, young lady seated with hands folded, checkered dress. Carte de visite., circa 1865 (Box 11, Folder 331)
      2-cent revenue stamp attached verso
      Item #D-18
    - Studio unknown Cameo portrait of man within green oval; buttons on vest open. partly tinted carte de visite, circa 1870 (Box 11, Folder 332)
      Item #D-19
    - Hugenot Gallery of Art, (Newkirk Building), Division Street, Rondout, NY Cameo portrait of young man, white shirt and velvet collar, gold chain. Carte de visite, circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 333)
      Item #D-20
    - D. Hinkle, Photographer, No. 4739 Main Street, Germantown (PA) Three quarter length double portrait, Caroline De Beilem Lovett, and Eliza; black lady in polka dot dress and bandanna, seated; white female child in white lace dress with sash seated in her lap. Carte de visite, circa 1870 (Box 11, Folder 334)
      Verso, in pencil. "Caroline De Beilem Lovett at 18 months old. + Eliza"
      Item #D-21
    - F. Forshew, Hudson, NY Cameo portrait of Rev. C.E. Crispell, man with white beard, wearing glasses. Carte de visite, 1876 (Box 11, Folder 335)
      In ink, verso: "Rev. C.E. Crispell, D.D., Professor in Hope College, Mich. June 21. 1876."
      Item #D-22
    - Bushby & Hart, 108 Broad Street, Lynn, MA Cameo portrait of lady with long earrings, striped dress, fancy bow with brooch. Carte de visite, circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 336)
      Item #D-23
    - S. Roe, Photographer, Cor. Prince & Prospect Sts., Flushing, L.I. (NY) Three quarter length double portrait, elderly black man in tuxedo holding white infant in christening gown. Carte de visite, circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 337)
      Very rare subject, black man, instead of nanny, holding white child.
      Item #D-24
    - Collins, Photograph Rooms, Bucksport, ME Full length group portrait: five children of various ages, standing, appears to be 3 boys, 2 girls. Carte de visite, circa 1875 (Box 11, Folder 338)
      Item #D-25
    - W.P. Kendall, Woodstock, VT Three quarter length portrait, young man one quarter left, face forward; seated with stripe on trousers. Carte de visite, circa 1868 (Box 11, Folder 339)
      Item #D-26
    - E.R. Gates, Photographer, Woodstock, VT Full length portrait; young lady seated plaid dress with ruffles. Carte de visite, circa 1870 (Box 11, Folder 340)
      Item #D-27
    - E.R. Gates, Photographer, Woodstock, VT Full length portrait, young girl standing beside prop tree trunk; fancy dress with lace and ruffles. Carte de visite, circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 341)
      Item #D-28
    - L. A. Spafard, Photographer, Main Street, near the Post Office, Norwich, CT Half length portrait, young lady seated wearing velvet blouse with large buttons. Carte de visite, circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 342)
      Item #D-29
    - A.B. Gardner, 125 Genesee St., Utica, NY Three quarter length portrait, young man standing wearing Masonic apron and collar. Carte de visite, circa 1875 (Box 11, Folder 343)
      Item #D-30
    - H.C. Phillips, and Bro., N.W. Cor. Ninth & Chestnut Sts., Philadelphia. H.C. Phillips, R.R. Phillips Half length portrait, young black woman seated with white baby. Woman wears hair net, brooch at throat. Carte de visite, circa 1870 (Box 11, Folder 344)
      In pencil, verso: "Wendell Phillips Family - Album." Below, "Geo. C. Phillips and his Nanny." Wendell Phillips, along with William Lloyd Garrison are the two most famous abolitionists of the nineteenth century.
      Item #D-31
    - Sedgwick & Lewis, Photographers, Ithaca, NY Cameo portrait, young man in suit with bowtie. Carte de visite, circa 1868 (Box 11, Folder 345)
      Item #D-32
    - Isaac Erb, 13 Charlotte Street, St. John, N.B. Oval portrait of young lady wearing a button jacket. Carte de visite, circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 346)
      Item #D-33
    - Studio unknown Bust length oval portrait; man with long hair in three piece suit, in fancy cartouche with tassels, Carte de visite, circa 1868 (Box 11, Folder 347)
      Item #D-34
    - W.P. Kendall, Photographer, Woodstock, VT Full length portrait, lady standing, long black dress, left hand on chair back, holding white handkerchief in right hand. Carte de visite, circa 1867 (Box 11, Folder 348)
      Item #D-35
    - Miley, Lexington, VA Bust portrait, young man with sideburns in three piece suit and fancy striped tie. Carte de visite, circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 349)
      Item #D-36
    - Theim, Photographer, 466 Broad St., Newark, NJ Bust portrait, young man in suit with large bow tie. Carte de visite, circa 1875 (Box 11, Folder 350)
      Item #D-37
    - Charles D. Fredericks & Co., 587 Broadway, New York, NY Full length portrait, shoe shine boy sitting on balustrade railing with shoe shine box, wearing cap, visor to the side. Carte de visite, circa 1868 (Box 11, Folder 351)
      Item #D-38
    - Wheeler, Photographer, Ottawa, IL Cameo portrait, man in suit with bow tie, flowing goatee. Carte de visite, circa 1880 (Box 11, Folder 352)
      Item #D-39
    - Studio unknown Full length portrait, young man with moustache and goatee, hand resting on table. Carte de visite, circa 1865 (Box 11, Folder 353)
      Item #D-40
    - Studio unknown Full length portrait, man in suit, full length coat, arm resting on elaborately designed chair. Carte de visite, circa 1865-68 (Box 11, Folder 354)
      Item #D-41
    - J.H. Hillman, Photographer, Canandaigua, NY Half length portrait, elderly gentleman seated: sideburns, suit, black bow tie. Carte de visite, circa 1875 (Box 11, Folder 355)
      Item #D-42